now let's talk about what happens in a
write-back cache right through is fairly
simple we just send rights to memory and
the cache works just as we described it
before but for right back caches we can
have a block that we did right since we
lost brought it from the memory in that
case when we replace the block we need
to write it to memory but we can have a
block that we didn't write since we lost
brought it from memory that block has
only been read since we brought it in in
that case when we replace there is no
need to write that block back to memory
but how do we know which one of these we
have one choice that we might make is
that we don't want to know we'll just
write every time that we replace the
block unfortunately there is a lot of
read-only stuff that we will now end up
writing to memory over and over although
it's unnecessary so instead we choose to
add a dirty bit to every block in the
cache the dirty bit says whether we have
written the block since it was placed in
the cache or not so if the dirty bit is
zero it means that the block is clean or
it was not written since it was last
brought from memory or we can have the
dirty bit big one in which case we say
that the block is dirty or it was
written since we last brought it from
memory and that means that we need to
write this block back to memory on
replacement when this block is kicked
out of the cache it needs to be written
to memory if it's clean then we don't
have to write it to memory